<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Victor S. Melo</title>
    <link>https://victor.dev.br/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Victor S. Melo</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Nov 2020 16:58:25 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://victor.dev.br/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Swift Failable Initializer</title>
      <link>https://victor.dev.br/posts/swift-failable-initializer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Nov 2020 16:58:25 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://victor.dev.br/posts/swift-failable-initializer/</guid>
      <description>Swift: Failable Initializer Consider the case below:
final class Human { let name: String var age: Int init(name: String, age: Int) { self.name = name self.age = age } } This is a simple class that represents a human being. At a first glance, we may not see any problem in this definition… or do we?
To understand the problems, we can play with the boundaries values. (This is a technique widely used in software testing).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processes and Threads</title>
      <link>https://victor.dev.br/posts/processes-threads/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2020 15:42:50 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://victor.dev.br/posts/processes-threads/</guid>
      <description>In this article, I present an overview about processes and threads.
Processes A process can be explained as “a program being executed“.
A process is not a program. You can have n processes for the same program. For example, when you open a tab in Chrome, it creates a new process called Google Chrome Helper (Renderer). So, Google Chrome can have multiple processes.
In the image above, I have multiple Chrome processes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello, World!</title>
      <link>https://victor.dev.br/posts/my-first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 16:45:04 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://victor.dev.br/posts/my-first-post/</guid>
      <description>Hello! My name is Victor and I&amp;rsquo;m an iOS consultant at ThoughtWorks, and a computer science undergraduate student at Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil.
I&amp;rsquo;ve been using a personal website since 2017, but it was more like a &amp;ldquo;web business card&amp;rdquo;, showing my projects, social media, and so on.
Now I want to use this space to share content. The topics will be about anything I find interesting in my &amp;ldquo;computer scientist world&amp;rdquo;, that includes software engineering topics I learn in my daily work at ThoughtWorks, content I found interesting in my college classes, Apple platform development, and other related stuffs.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>